<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-24T23:15:31+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 6: The Case of the Invisible Notebook</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/the-case-of-the-invisible-notebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 6: The Case of the Invisible Notebook"/><published>2025-08-24T23:07:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-24T23:07:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/the-case-of-the-invisible-notebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/the-case-of-the-invisible-notebook/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-mission-from-analysis-to-exhibit">The Mission: From Analysis to Exhibit</h3> <p>Every data investigation culminates in a single moment: presenting the evidence. For the past several sessions, I’ve been deep in the trenches with a new subject, <strong>Maven Fuzzy Factory</strong>. I interrogated their entire business history, running a battery of SQL queries and Python visualizations to map their journey from a struggling startup to a data-driven powerhouse. The result was a comprehensive report, a complete case file detailing every breakthrough and every misstep.</p> <p>The mission for today was to get this evidence admitted to the record. This wasn’t just about another project page; it was about showcasing the entire analytical process. The plan was ambitious: embed the raw evidence—the Jupyter Notebook itself—directly into the portfolio. It would be the ultimate proof of work, a transparent look into the machinery of my investigation.</p> <h3 id="the-crime-scene-a-blank-space">The Crime Scene: A Blank Space</h3> <p>I followed the procedure. A new project page was created. The report was written up, the dashboards were added to a beautiful image slider, and the code to embed the notebook was put in place. I deployed.</p> <p>And I was met with a blank space. The report was there, but the notebook—the star witness—was a no-show. The system wasn’t throwing an error; it was just… empty. It was a perfectly executed disappearing act, and my job was to figure out how the trick was done.</p> <h3 id="the-investigation-chasing-down-leads">The Investigation: Chasing Down Leads</h3> <p>My first hypothesis was simple: <strong>a configuration error</strong>. The theme’s documentation—my field guide—showed that embedding notebooks required a special plugin. The evidence suggested I had hired the plugin but hadn’t put it on the payroll.</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Lead #1: The Payroll (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Gemfile</code> &amp; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code>).</strong> I cracked open the site’s core configuration files. Sure enough, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll-jupyter-notebook</code> plugin was missing from the active roster. I added it to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Gemfile</code> and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code> file. This was the equivalent of giving my new specialist a security badge and access to the building. I redeployed, confident I had my man. Still nothing.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Lead #2: The Missing Expert.</strong> This is where the case got interesting. My “specialist” plugin was on-site, but the notebook was still missing. I started to think about the system as a whole. The plugin’s job isn’t to <em>understand</em> the notebook; its job is to <em>find someone who can</em>. It’s a translator, not a linguist. It needed to hand the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.ipynb</code> file off to the real expert: <strong>Jupyter</strong> itself.</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="the-breakthrough-unmasking-the-conspiracy">The Breakthrough: Unmasking the Conspiracy</h3> <p>The truth was a classic case of a communication breakdown. My Jekyll site (the agency) had successfully hired the plugin (the translator), but the translator had no one to talk to because the expert (Jupyter) wasn’t in its contact list.</p> <p>Even though Jupyter was installed on my machine, the Jekyll environment didn’t know how to find it. The entire system was working perfectly in isolation, but the critical link between the Ruby-based Jekyll world and the Python-based Jupyter world was broken.</p> <p>The fix was to ensure the expert was on speed dial for everyone. A quick <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pip install jupyter nbconvert</code> made sure the tool was globally available, and a server restart re-established the lines of communication.</p> <h3 id="what-this-teaches-a-data-analyst">What This Teaches a Data Analyst</h3> <p>This entire investigation is a crucial lesson for any analyst. Your final report is only as good as the system that delivers it.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Understand the Full Stack:</strong> It’s not enough to just run the analysis in a notebook. You have to understand the entire pipeline, from the database to the Python environment to the web server. Every connection point is a potential point of failure.</li> <li><strong>Dependencies are Everything:</strong> My Jekyll site <em>depended</em> on a Ruby plugin, which in turn <em>depended</em> on a Python application. A data analyst who doesn’t understand the chain of dependencies will always be blindsided by errors that seem to come from nowhere.</li> <li><strong>The Error Log is Your Best Informant:</strong> When a system gives you the silent treatment, the build logs are where it confesses. Learning to read them is a non-negotiable skill.</li> </ul> <p>Today, we built a complete, end-to-end analytical showpiece and then debugged the very infrastructure it was built on. The case of the invisible notebook is closed.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technical-deep-dive"/><category term="portfolio-build"/><category term="jekyll"/><category term="jupyter"/><category term="data-visualization"/><category term="python"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A deep dive into the end-to-end analytical process, from raw data to a final report, and the hidden systems that tried to keep it offline.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Maven Market Case: A Deep Dive into the BI Workflow</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-five-the-maven-market-case/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Maven Market Case: A Deep Dive into the BI Workflow"/><published>2025-08-23T19:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-23T19:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-five-the-maven-market-case</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-five-the-maven-market-case/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-briefing-a-new-case-arrives">The Briefing: A New Case Arrives</h3> <p>Every data detective lives for the moment a new case file lands on their desk. This one came in the form of a folder of raw, disconnected CSV files from <strong>Maven Market</strong>, a multi-national grocery chain. The mission was clear, if not simple: infiltrate this chaotic mess of transactional data, interrogate it until it confessed its secrets, and build a dynamic dashboard that would serve as a single source of truth for the entire operation.</p> <p>This wasn’t just about making charts; it was about building an intelligence-gathering machine from the ground up.</p> <h3 id="the-investigation-following-the-data-trail">The Investigation: Following the Data Trail</h3> <p>A good investigation follows a strict procedure. You don’t just jump to conclusions. You build the case, piece by piece, from the ground up. This project was a live-fire exercise in the entire end-to-end business intelligence workflow.</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Connecting &amp; Shaping the Evidence (Power Query):</strong> The first step was to get the raw data into the interrogation room. I connected Power BI to a folder of CSVs containing thousands of transactions and returns. This data was messy—inconsistent formats, missing connections. Using Power Query, I cleaned it, merged files, and transformed the raw inputs into a set of clean, reliable tables. This is the unglamorous but most critical part of any analysis: ensuring the evidence is admissible.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Building the Relationship Map (Data Modeling):</strong> Once the individual pieces of evidence were clean, I had to understand how they connected. In the data modeling phase, I constructed a relational database, linking the transaction and returns data to lookup tables for customers, products, and stores. This is like building a crime board, connecting suspects to locations and motives. A well-built model ensures that when you ask a question in one part of the data, the answer is consistent everywhere else.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>The Interrogation (DAX Measures):</strong> With a solid model in place, the real interrogation began. I used DAX (Data Analysis Expressions) to create a battery of calculated measures. I wasn’t just counting transactions; I was calculating <strong>Profit Margin</strong>, <strong>Return Rate</strong>, and complex time-intelligence metrics like <strong>Year-to-Date Revenue</strong> and <strong>Revenue vs. Target</strong>. DAX is the language you use to ask the tough questions—the ones that reveal the real story hiding beneath the surface.</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="the-challenges-when-the-trail-goes-cold">The Challenges: When the Trail Goes Cold</h3> <p>No investigation is a straight line. This case presented its own set of challenges that required more than just technical skill; they required an analytical mindset.</p> <ul> <li><strong>The “Snowflake” Schema:</strong> The store data was connected to a separate regions table, creating a “snowflake” schema. This adds a layer of complexity to the model and requires careful management to ensure filters propagate correctly. It’s a reminder that real-world data is rarely simple.</li> <li><strong>Time-Intelligence Complexity:</strong> Calculating metrics like “60-Day Running Revenue” or comparing performance to the “Last Month” requires a deep understanding of DAX filter context. Writing these formulas is like crafting a perfectly worded legal argument—every comma and every function has to be precise, or you get the wrong answer.</li> </ul> <h3 id="what-this-project-proves">What This Project Proves</h3> <p>This project is more than a dashboard; it’s a demonstration of a complete analytical skill set.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Methodical Process:</strong> It proves I can follow a structured, end-to-end BI workflow, from raw data ingestion to final report delivery. This is the core discipline of any data professional.</li> <li><strong>Technical Proficiency:</strong> It showcases my hands-on skills in <strong>Power Query</strong> for ETL (Extract, Transform, Load), complex <strong>Data Modeling</strong> to build a reliable source of truth, and advanced <strong>DAX</strong> for creating meaningful, actionable metrics.</li> <li><strong>Business Acumen:</strong> The final dashboard, with its KPI cards and interactive filters, proves I can translate complex data into a tool that business leaders can actually use to make decisions. I didn’t just find the data; I made it talk.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="project-deep-dive"/><category term="portfolio-build"/><category term="power-bi"/><category term="data-modeling"/><category term="dax"/><category term="etl"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Deconstructing a full business intelligence project, from messy CSVs to a dynamic dashboard that uncovered the real story behind the sales data.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day Four: Creating a Project Amidst Chaos</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/creating-the-first-project-page/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day Four: Creating a Project Amidst Chaos"/><published>2025-08-21T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-21T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/creating-the-first-project-page</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/creating-the-first-project-page/"><![CDATA[<p>Today was supposed to be the day. The day I finally saw the portfolio live and working. Instead, it was a masterclass in frustration, courtesy of a complete outage on GitHub Actions. The build process for my site has been stuck in a “Queued” state for hours, a problem completely out of my hands. After trying to cancel and re-run the job to no avail, it became clear that no amount of troubleshooting on my end would fix it.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="pivoting-to-content">Pivoting to Content</h3> <p>Instead of waiting, we decided to shift focus to what I could actually control: the content. It was the perfect time to build out the first real project page for my portfolio—a showcase for a Power BI sales report I created for the AdventureWorks company.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="building-the-project-page">Building the Project Page</h3> <p>We started by creating a new file, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">10_project.md</code>, in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_projects</code> folder. The initial idea was just a simple page, but we quickly decided to make it more dynamic. A single static screenshot felt flat.</p> <p>The solution was to implement an interactive image swiper. We replaced the standard image code with a carousel that cycles through three different screenshots of the dashboard: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">r1.jpg</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">r2.jpg</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">r3.jpg</code>. This immediately made the page feel more engaging and allowed me to show off different aspects of the report at a glance.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="the-power-bi-embedding-challenge">The Power BI Embedding Challenge</h3> <p>The next major task was embedding the interactive Power BI report. I had the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">iframe</code> code ready to go, but we ran into a critical issue: the standard embed link requires the viewer to sign in to a Power BI account. This is a non-starter for a portfolio. A recruiter isn’t going to sign in to view my work.</p> <p>The correct method is to use the “Publish to web (public)” feature, which creates a link that anyone can view. But, of course, that option was missing from my Power BI account. After digging into the settings, it became clear that the feature was disabled by an administrator policy, another roadblock.</p> <p>With a true public embed off the table, we had to pivot again. A broken or inaccessible <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">iframe</code> is worse than no embed at all. We scrapped the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">iframe</code> entirely and replaced it with a simple, clean text link that says “here.” It’s an honest solution that directs visitors to the report without the friction of a failed embed.</p> <p>So, while the site itself remains in limbo, a major piece of it is now fully built and ready. We turned a day of technical delays into a productive session that resulted in a much better, more thoughtful project page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="career-development"/><category term="portfolio-building"/><category term="github-pages"/><category term="jekyll"/><category term="power-bi"/><category term="troubleshooting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With the website's build process completely stuck, we pivoted to building out the first real project page, facing new challenges with Power BI along the way.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Portfolio, Day 3: The Devil is in the Details</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-three-the-last-mile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portfolio, Day 3: The Devil is in the Details"/><published>2025-08-20T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-20T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-three-the-last-mile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-three-the-last-mile/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-mission-achieving-total-consistency">The Mission: Achieving Total Consistency</h3> <p>Days one and two were about broad strokes: setting up the framework, writing the content, and fixing the major bugs. Day three was about something more difficult: the last mile. It’s the point where you stop building and start polishing. It’s the obsessive, detail-oriented work that most people skip, and it’s the only thing that matters.</p> <p>The new mission was to overhaul my CV page. The data was a mess of placeholders, and the layout had inconsistencies that, to a data detective’s eye, were as jarring as a fraudulent transaction.</p> <h3 id="data-integrity-the-first-priority">Data Integrity: The First Priority</h3> <p>The first task was a data overhaul inside the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">resume.json</code> file. This is the central database for my professional history, and its integrity is non-negotiable.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Work History:</strong> I translated every role from my career into the precise JSON structure, focusing on quantifiable achievements.</li> <li><strong>Education &amp; Certifications:</strong> I updated my academic and professional credentials, ensuring every date was correct and every issuer was named. For my university degree, I made a strategic choice to highlight its official recognition in Germany—a key piece of data for my target audience.</li> </ul> <p>This wasn’t just data entry; it was about ensuring the source of truth was clean, accurate, and structured.</p> <h3 id="the-final-boss-a-single-inconsistent-section">The Final Boss: A Single Inconsistent Section</h3> <p>With the data clean, a glaring visual bug remained. The “Certificates” section was rendered as a grid of cards, while “Work” and “Education” were clean, professional lists. It was a design flaw that broke the flow of the entire page. It had to be fixed.</p> <p>What followed was a frustrating but invaluable lesson in front-end debugging.</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>The Wrong Path:</strong> My first instinct was to fight fire with fire. I wrote custom CSS to override the grid layout. The result? The CSS was either too weak and was ignored, or too strong and broke the entire page. It was a classic case of treating the symptom, not the disease.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>The Root Cause Analysis:</strong> A true analyst doesn’t just fix a problem; they understand its origin. I dove into the theme’s source code and found the real culprit: the HTML blueprint itself (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_includes/resume/certificates.liquid</code>). It was fundamentally different from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">work.liquid</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">education.liquid</code> blueprints.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Re-engineering the Solution:</strong> The only way to guarantee perfect consistency was to use the same blueprint. I meticulously re-engineered the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">certificates.liquid</code> file, using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">education.liquid</code> file as a reference. I went line-by-line, matching every HTML tag, every CSS class, and every variable.</p> </li> </ol> <p>The result is a CV page where every section is now visually harmonious. It was a brutal, detail-obsessed fight for a few pixels of alignment, and it was worth it. This is what it means to be a data professional: an obsessive, relentless pursuit of getting it right, down to the last detail.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technical-deep-dive"/><category term="portfolio-build"/><category term="front-end-dev"/><category term="css"/><category term="debugging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The final 10% of any project is what separates the amateur from the professional. A deep dive into the obsessive pursuit of consistency.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Portfolio, Day 2: The Debugging Chronicles</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-two-the-debugging-chronicles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portfolio, Day 2: The Debugging Chronicles"/><published>2025-08-18T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-18T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-two-the-debugging-chronicles</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/portfolio-day-two-the-debugging-chronicles/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-strategy-ruthless-optimization">The Strategy: Ruthless Optimization</h3> <p>Day one was about laying the foundation. Day two? It was about sharpening the blade. I looked at my homepage not as a biography, but as the opening argument in a case to a very busy jury: potential employers.</p> <p>The verdict was swift. The “News” and “Publications” sections were circumstantial evidence at best—distractions. In their place, I needed to present Exhibit A, my proof of work. I decided to surgically remove the noise and engineer a new section front and center: <strong>“Featured Projects.”</strong> This wasn’t just a design choice; it was a strategic decision to control the narrative and immediately answer the only question that matters: “Can you do the job?”</p> <h3 id="the-crime-scene-the-case-of-the-empty-section">The Crime Scene: The Case of the Empty Section</h3> <p>I coded the new section. I configured it. I deployed it. And… nothing. An empty space where my proudest work should have been. This is where a data detective’s real work begins. The system wasn’t throwing errors; it was giving me the silent treatment. The most frustrating kind of bug.</p> <p>My investigation led me down a rabbit hole of dead-end hypotheses:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>The Wrong Sorting Key:</strong> My first assumption was a simple logic error. I was trying to sort projects by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">date</code>, but the theme was hardcoded to use a number called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">importance</code>. A quick change, a redeploy, and… still nothing.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>The Data Type Mismatch:</strong> I dug deeper into the code. The sorting logic was looking for projects where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">importance</code> was equal to the <em>text</em> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">"1"</code>, but my project files correctly defined it as the <em>number</em> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1</code>. To a computer, that’s like comparing a photograph of a key to the key itself. They are not the same. I corrected the data type. I redeployed. Still nothing.</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="the-breakthrough-finding-the-real-culprit">The Breakthrough: Finding the Real Culprit</h3> <p>At this point, I knew I wasn’t just fixing a typo. I was hunting a fundamental flaw in the system’s logic. The final breakthrough came when I realized the theme was using two entirely different visual blueprints for projects: a vertical card for the main projects page, and a horizontal one for the homepage.</p> <p>The sorting file I was fixing was correctly gathering the data, but it was handing that data off to the wrong blueprint. It was like a perfectly executed police raid on the wrong address.</p> <p>With the true culprit identified, the fix was decisive. I rewrote the sorting logic from the ground up to be more robust and, critically, to use the correct <strong>horizontal card blueprint</strong>. I redeployed.</p> <p>Success.</p> <h3 id="what-this-teaches-a-data-analyst">What This Teaches a Data Analyst</h3> <p>This entire ordeal—the strategic pivot, the frustrating bugs, the forensic deep-dive into the code—is a perfect metaphor for the daily life of a data analyst. You start with a clear goal, you hit a wall of confusing or missing data, and you must apply logic, discipline, and relentless curiosity to find the truth. The answer is never on the surface. You have to be willing to get your hands dirty in the source code of the problem.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technical-deep-dive"/><category term="portfolio-build"/><category term="debugging"/><category term="jekyll"/><category term="liquid"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes the most valuable data is in the error logs. A recap of Day 2, where strategy met a series of stubborn bugs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My First Steps in Building a Data Analyst Portfolio</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/building-my-data-analyst-portfolio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Steps in Building a Data Analyst Portfolio"/><published>2025-08-17T21:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-17T21:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/building-my-data-analyst-portfolio</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2025/building-my-data-analyst-portfolio/"><![CDATA[<swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/p1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/p1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/p1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/p1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/p2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/p2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/p2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/p2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <hr/> <h3 id="introduction-giving-my-data-a-voice">Introduction: Giving My Data a Voice</h3> <p>A resume is a police sketch of my skills – it gives you the basic features, but it’s flat, lifeless. It tells you <em>that</em> I can wrangle a dataset into submission, but it doesn’t show you the exhilarating treasure hunt that got me there. I decided I needed more than a sketch; I needed a living, breathing crime board where I could pin up my findings, connect the dots, and show the world the stories my data is screaming to tell. This portfolio is that crime board. It’s where the outliers and the “why” behind the numbers get to take center stage.</p> <h3 id="the-tool-i-chose-al-folio-my-digital-detectives-office">The Tool I Chose: al-folio, My Digital Detective’s Office</h3> <p>Every data detective needs a workspace. Mine is a Jekyll theme called <strong>al-folio</strong>. I didn’t pick it because it was flashy; I picked it because it gets out of the way. It’s the clean, uncluttered desk that lets the evidence shine. No distracting bells and whistles, no bloated code to sift through. It’s brutally efficient and lets me focus on what actually matters: torturing the data until it confesses its secrets. It’s less of a website theme and more of a precision instrument, and it was the perfect choice for an analyst who believes in substance over style.</p> <h3 id="the-configuration-process-hacking-the-mainframe">The Configuration Process: Hacking the Mainframe</h3> <p>Getting this portfolio off the ground felt like getting root access to a new system. It was a thrilling dive into the backend, pulling levers and flipping switches to make it my own.</p> <ul> <li><strong>The Master Control (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code>):</strong> The first stop was the main configuration file. Think of it as the site’s central nervous system. I didn’t just fill in the blanks; I calibrated it, tuning the parameters to control everything from my site’s title to its core plugins.</li> <li><strong>The Mission Statement (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_pages/about.md</code>):</strong> My “About” page isn’t a biography; it’s a manifesto. It’s the “why” behind my what. It’s where I lay out my philosophy on data and give fair warning about my obsessive curiosity.</li> <li><strong>The Rap Sheet (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_data/cv.yml</code>):</strong> Forget the boring resume format. I chose the YAML file to build my CV because it’s structured, clean, and reads like a well-documented script. It’s my professional history, refactored for clarity.</li> <li><strong>The Case Files (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_projects</code>):</strong> This is the heart of the operation. Each project gets its own file in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_projects</code> directory. These aren’t just descriptions; they’re the case files of my investigations, detailing the messy beginnings, the “aha!” moments, and the final, actionable insights.</li> </ul> <h3 id="why-this-matters-for-a-data-analyst-more-than-just-code">Why This Matters for a Data Analyst: More Than Just Code</h3> <p>Let’s be clear: building this wasn’t just a weekend project. It was a masterclass in the very skills I use every day to hunt down insights.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Technical Chops:</strong> You can’t build this without getting your hands dirty with Git, GitHub, and Markdown. This is the stuff that separates the amateurs from the pros. It’s about version control that saves your skin when a query goes wrong and documentation that actually makes sense six months from now.</li> <li><strong>Translating Geek to English:</strong> My job is to make complex data understandable to people who don’t have time to care about the standard deviation. Writing these posts, explaining my projects – it’s the ultimate practice in turning a statistically significant result into a story that makes a stakeholder sit up and listen.</li> <li><strong>The Proof is in the Portfolio:</strong> A resume says “I can build predictive models.” My portfolio <em>shows</em> you the model, lets you play with the inputs, and demonstrates its scary-good accuracy. It’s a live-fire exercise, not a theoretical claim.</li> </ul> <h3 id="conclusion-the-hunt-is-on">Conclusion: The Hunt is On</h3> <p>The lab is built, the tools are sharpened, and the first few case files are up on the board. But this is just the beginning. This portfolio is a living entity, a place where I’ll be documenting every new data mystery I unravel. It’s where I’ll get to be unapologetically obsessive about the patterns others miss.</p> <p>I’ve spent countless hours wrestling with datasets just because I had to know what they were trying to tell me. Now, I have a place to share the answers.</p> <p>Warning: I might get a little too excited explaining why your data trends the way it does. Ready to stop guessing and start knowing?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="career-development"/><category term="portfolio"/><category term="data-analysis"/><category term="jekyll"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A look into the tools, configurations, and the value of creating a personal portfolio for a data analyst.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024 We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://anasakhomach.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[<h3>External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</h3> <p>If you prefer publishing blog posts on medium.com or other external sources, starting version v0.5.0, <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> lets you to display your external posts in the blog feed of your website! 🎉🎉</p> <p>Configuring external sources of super simple. After upgrading to v0.5.0, just add the following section to your _config.yml:</p> <pre>external_sources:<br />  - name: medium.com  # name of the source (arbitrary string)<br />    rss_url: <a href="https://medium.com/@al-folio/feed">https://medium.com/@&lt;your-medium-username&gt;/feed</a></pre> <p>The example above adds your medium.com blog post feed as an external source. But you can add arbitrary RSS feeds as sources.</p> <p>Any questions or suggestions? 👉 Start <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions">a discussion on GitHub</a>!</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b60a1d241a0a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>